Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 6 -- Letters to Franklin 1781-1782 Mss.B.F85inventory06
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 6 -- Letters to Franklin
1781-1782
Mss.B.F85inventory06
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
1269 items
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Mante, Thomas. Sceaux
    Scope and Contents note
    Desires to serve America; in a continual state of want; applies to Franklin for aid.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Poellnitz, baron von H. H. de
    New Year congratulations.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Marcorelle, -------. Narbonne
    Publishes a semi-weekly political and scientific periodical; sends the last number with an account of Franklin.
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 1; L.S. Sam[uel] Huntington, President. 2p.; Huntington, Samuel
    Instructions for procuring a further loan in France. Mission of Col. [John] Laurens.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 526; Blgelow, VII, 183).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    England's manifesto of Dec. 20th, declaring war on Holland. The English church at The Hague burnt; motives unknown. His approaching departure for The Hague with Messrs. Adams and Searle.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 1; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Wishes for the New Year.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, October, 1906, 35.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 2; A.L.S. Fra[nci]s Lewis, in behalf of the Board. 3p.; The Board of Admiralty. Philadelphia
    Requests information in regard to a late expedition commanded by John Paul Jones, in which the frigate "Alliance" took part; especially as to the ownership of the other ships, any previous agreement as to the distribution of proceeds from prizes, the amount of proceeds, the benefits received by the United states, the dispute between John Paul Jones and Captain Landais, and as to the "Alliance" since her arrival in French waters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 2; A.L.S. 2p.; Bondfield, John. Bordeaux
    Announcing the arrival of a vessel from Annapolis; news of the landing made by the English at Hampton and their precipitare retreat owing to a body of French troops having landed at Georgetown, South Carolina; Lord Cornwallis confined to a small circuit around Charlestown.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 3; A.L.S. 1p.; Franks, David Salisbury. L'Orient
    The "St. James" to sail by the 15th inst.; will be ready to embark as soon as he receives his instructions.
    General note
    1 For Autobiographical Sketch see Pub. of Am. Jewish Historical Sec., X, 101.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 3; A.L.S. 3p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Concerning the business so admirably adjusted by the Hon. Thomas Barclay, Consul-General in France for America. States several instances proving the Dutch Republic's good will toward America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 4; A.L.S. 3p.; Marbois, François Barbé de. Philadelphia
    Exertions of Mrs. Bache in procuring supplies of clothing for the American soldiers; Rivington's efforts to turn her zeal into ridicule.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition note
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 527; Bigelow, VII, 188).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Fleury and Demadières. Orleans
    Delighted that the wine arrived in good condition; have just shipped a cask of the old wine of St. Denis, according to orders.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Auzoüer, —, marquise d'. Chataudoin
    His wife most eager for news of her cousin, Charles Carroll, from whom she has not heard for nine years.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 5; A.L.S. 3p.; Bordot, François. La Rochelle
    Seeks the position of American agent at Rochelle; movements of the Cadiz fleet.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 5; D.S. Charles Thomson, Sec[retar]y, and attested. 1p.; The Continental Congress
    Resolution that bills of exchange amounting to £12,000 be drawn on the American Minister at Versailles for the purchase of clothing for the Jersey line.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 6; D.S. John L. Clarkson, Sec[retar]y, pro tem. 2p.; The Board of Treasury. Philadelphia
    Order carrying out the preceding Resolutions of Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Ceintrè, Poulain de. Near Angers
    Wishes a position as Lieurenant or Captain in a Boston regiment.
    A.E. by Franklin. It is impossible.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Lausanne
    Enclosing an account of a volunteer review in Ireland, which his father asked him to forward.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Zrény, Baron. Kaschau, Hungary
    At the slightest word of encouragement, will resign his position, say farwell to his friends and present himself at Passy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 9; L.S. 1p.; Willson, John and Stephen Hamson
    Have been prisoners since October, 1780; penniless and almost naked; entreat Franklin to procure them their liberty.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Hodgson, William. London
    Acknowledging £150 to be applied to the relief of the American prisoners; the weekly allowance suggested by Franklin will amount to £150 per month, as there are five hundred prisoners; if this sum can be furnished regularly, well and good; but until he has orders to that effect, he will feel justified in distrubuting less.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Waterhouse, Benjamin. Leyden
    Wrote a few weeks ago enclosing letters from Dr. Fothergill; little thought that he would so soon have to announce his death, which took place on the 26th of December; his director, guide and friend.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 10; L.S. 1p.; Bertrand, -----. Paris
    Transcribing his letter of September 29, 1780; attributes receiving no reply to Franklin's illness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 10; A.L.S. 1p.; All, Isaac. L'Orient
    Leaves for Philadelphia in a few days; hopes to be entrusted with a letter for Dr. Franklin's family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Gébelin, Antoine Court de. Paris
    Introducing M. La Renaudière, who, hearing that a printer is wanted in the United States capable of training apprentices, would like the position.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 11; A.L.S. 2p.; Bowdoin, James. Boston
    Wrote some months before by Mr. Guild, who probably spoke of a bill then pending in the Assembly for incorporating a philosophical society; it is now formed under the name of the Amercian Academy of Arts and Sciences; at the last meeting several distinguished gentlemen were put in nomination, among them the Amercian Ambassador to the Court of France; forwards a specimen of Society's first fruit.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 12; A.L.S 1 p.; Der Kenne, Louis, Liège
    Offering two hundred and thirty muskets at a reasonable price.
    A.E. by Franklin. Has no need of them.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 12; A.L.S. 2 p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Russia strongly for Holland and against Great Britain. Letters of marque against England being generally distributed to privateers and armed vessels.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 12; A.L.S 2 p.; Newenham, Sir Edward. Dublin
    The citizens of Dublin, touched by the present situation in the West Indies, desire to send provisions and clothing; desire a passport and protection for their vessel, as well as Franklin's interest in obtaining the same from the Court of France and the Spanish Ambassador at Paris.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 13; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Macarty, Mr & Mrs
    Sorry they cannot dine with him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 13; D.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas. Paris
    Certifying that he has not disposed of any of the within mentioned certificates and that he has deposited the power of attorney sent him by Mr. Shee with Dr. Franklin.
    (Copy.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Durand, ------
    Concerning a note forwarded to him by a book seller in Turin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Fletcher, John. Ostend
    Introducing Mr. Charles Hill of Bristol, who has helped many Americans in England; he is going to Bilbao on business, and being English born, he will need a passport from the Spanish Ambassador; begs Franklin's interest in obtaining this favor; such services instrumental in encouraging a humane attitude towards American prisoners in England.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 15; Mem. 1p.; Lafargue, Mme. Passy
    Account for wages, etc., as cook for Dr. Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] January 15; A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; Grosley, Pierre Jean
    Has not forgotten the pleasure he had of seeing Franklin in London at Sir John Pringle's. Desires to see him now about a matter connected with the Royal Society of London.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 16; A.L.S. 1p.; Aubin de St. Lambert, G
    Hopes for a private audience with Franklin; his former position as Commander of the Royal Frigates.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Duchemin, Daniel. Amiens
    Grateful for the position offered him, but cannot leave his wife and daughter; if circumstances should alter, relies on the continuance of Franklin's favor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 19; A.L.S. 2p.; Franquelin, -----. Hesdin
    Asks Franklin's interest to procure him the position of agent on one of the King's farms.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Rabiqueau, -----
    Sending a prospectus of interest to a lover of the arts and sciences.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 22; A.L.S. 1p.; John de Neufville and Son. Amsterdam
    Announcing that the Dutch states have joined the armed neutrality which was signed at the Court of Prussia; force and spirit shown by the Dutch in regard to English demands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 22; A.L.S. 3p.; Grandclos, ----, baron (?) de. St Prix
    Desires directions for converting smoke into flame; understands that Franklin, when he invented his stove, employed a certain method to this end; has failed to find an account of it among his works.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 22; A.L.S. 6p.; Laboureau, Mme. Franklin. Paris
    Grateful for Franklin's kindness. Has lost everything through the failure of the firm; begs Franklin to procure employment for her husband.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; D'aubenton, -----. Paris
    Forwards a memoir concerning certain people in the King's service; begs Franklin to procure him information on this subject.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Conkling, Joseph. La Rochelle
    His brig the "Whim" ready to receive her cargo; fears that the proceeds from the sale of his tobacco will be insufficient to load the brig; begs Franklin's influence with the Secretary of State to allow him to carry freight from the King's stores to M. de Ternay's fleet at Rhode Island. Any despatches may be safely confided to his care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Progress of negotiations between Russia and Holland; England's vain efforts to keep Holland out of the Alliance. Desires confirmation of certain cheering news from America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781 January 24?]; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Daschkow, Princess. Paris
    Enclosing a letter addressed to Franklin which her daughter received from England; reason why the seal was broken; desirous of making his acquaintance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 24; A.L.S. John Gibson, Jr., President. 2p.; The Board of Treasury. Philadelphia
    Warning as to a number of lost sets of bills of exchange.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Efforts made by Sir [James] Harris, the English Ambassador at St. Petersburg, to keep Holland out of an alliance with Russia; attitude of the Empress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Genet, -----. Paris
    Request from Capt. [William] Robeson for a passage to America on board one of the King's ships.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Deans, Silas. Antwerp
    Situation of Antwerp admirable for commerce, though that as well as politics appears to have been banished.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent, 1743-1794
    Has just heard that the shipment of saltpetre from St. Malo to L'Orient has terminated successfully; offers his congratulations. Has sustained a heavy below in the loss of an aunt who had been a second mother to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 27; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Dana, Francis M. Paris
    Accepting invitation to dinner.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Nogaret, François-Félix
    Hopes Franklin has regained health. Asks him to accept as a gift the portrait of the Archbishop of Paris which will soon be engraved and delivered to him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 29; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Searle, James. Paris
    Unable to accept his invitation to dinner as he is engaged to M. de Beaumarchais.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 29; A.L.S. 1p.; Daubert, -----. Caen
    Enclosing a sonnet (1 p.) of which Franklin is the subject; written in honor of the Immaculate Conception; it won the first prize at the University of Caen.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Holland's manifesto not yet published; fears the consequence of so much delay. Holland likely to ask of France aid for her forces in the East Indies.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] January 30; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Daschkow, Princess. Paris
    Acknowledging Franklin's kind note and appointing a day when she will be happy to see him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Lenoir, Jean-Charles-Pierre. Paris
    Enclosing the desired permission, that the books held at the customhouse may be delivered to Franklin's address without further delay.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 31; The American Academy of Arts and Sciences. Boston
    Certificate of membership.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 January 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    Have paid the desired amount to Capt. Nicholas Broughton of Marblehead. The ship "Marquis de la Fayette" not yet appeared.
  - to Jean-Baptists de Roy, 1781 February 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Deshautesrayes, -----. Collège Royal
    His cousin is a printer who desires to pursue his trade in Boston; answers for his intelligence and abillity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Chastellux, François-Jean de Beauvoir, chevalier de. Newport
    Praises Mr. Laurens in the highest terms. Franklin's letters of introduction procured him the kindest welcome in Philadelphia, from Mr. Reed and the Academical Society.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Since his last a ship loaded with sugar and cotton from Port au Prince (but belonging to Boston) arrived at l'Orient to his address. Each post informs him that the ship ["Marquis de la Fayette"] is ready but she is, notwithstanding, still at Bordeaux. If he had not made the bargain for her he could now ship the goods in American bottoms as there are two or three ships at l'Orient. Has sent M. de Chaumont his account current by this day's post. If Dr. Franklin takes this clothing he will repay Mr. de Chaumont by him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 1; A.L.S. 5p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    For news of the state of affairs, refers him to Col. [John] Laurens an officer in the army and son of former President Laurens, now a prisoner in the Tower of London; Col. Laurens's mission probably connected with the great need of money. Greater degree of unanimity in the settlement of the new Constitution. Has long expected the arrival of Capt. Jones in the "Ariel"; doubts not he will clear himself of all charges against him; Landais's trial and the testimony of the officers and passengers. Franklin elected a member of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences. The bearer of the present letter is his son-in-law, Col. Johonnot, late of the U.S. army, who goes to France to see his son; will appreciate any kindness shown them. Encloses a memoir, of which he is the author, concerning the great service rendered the American cause by Count d'Estaing; wishes it printed and published at his expense; encloses copies of his sermon delivered at the inauguration of their new Commonwealth.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 1; A. L. S. 3 p.; Cottier, -----. Doullens
    Saw in the Pennsylvania Gazette of Oct. 30th, some mention of the Chevalier du Buisson; his only surviving daughter is very anxious for news of her father, who went to America in 1757 and of whom nothing has been heard since.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 1; A. L. S. 4 p.; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves, marquis de, 1757-1834
    Fears that party feeling will long delay the choice of a Secretary for Franklin's Embassy. Mission of Col. Laurens; approves his selection by Congress. Has sent, from time to time, authentic and accurate accounts of their successes, but dared not give a confidential account of their extreme need of money, arms,clothing, and ammunition. French force of great service in counteracting the enemy's plans. Col. Laurens can furnish all particulars of a public and private character. His own situation in America is the happiest he can ever hope to obtain. Not surprised to discover that Franklin has enemies, but the people at large revere his name. Does not know whether their little book has yet made its appearance; enemy's hellish trade will furnish him with further material, which he will forward.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 1; A. L. S. 1 p.; Newenham, Thomas. Brussels
    The books which the bearer will deliver, were given him by his uncle, Sir Edward Newenham; has also a letter from his uncle which he will deliver in person.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Cooper, Samuel. Boston
    Introducing [Louis Dominique Ethis] de Corney, a member of several literary societies in Europe, who came to America with Marquis de la Fayette on public business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 3; A.L.S. 1 p.; Coffyn, Francis. Dunkirk
    The bearer is Mr. Thomas Wynne, who escaped with his young brother from an English prison; their hope of sailing to America from one of the French seaports; has lent them a little money; leaves the rest to Franklin's known kindness.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 5; A.L.S. 3 p.; Dumas, C.G.F.
    Sending enclosure for Congress. Talk of a general peace through the interventions of Russia; report that England has proposed a nine years' truce to France. Delighted to see Mr. Silas Deane. Account of his conversation with Mr. Searle and the French Ambassador. Conference between the Ambassador and M. G[illo]n; the latter's belief that he will soon be able to see sail from the Texel. Desiring to know if there is any Minister in Europe with sufficient power from Congress to enter into negotiations with Russia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 5; A.L.S. 1 p.; Gourlade and Moylan. L'Orient
    The arms damaged on board the "Ariel" and left for repair are nearly ready for shipping; desires to know if they are to go on board the "Marquis de la Fayette."
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Jourdan, ------. Troyes
    Has several talents which he thinks will prove advantageous to the Colony of Boston.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Wrote some weeks before of experiments done according to Franklin's directions, with wires of various metals. Repeats his inquires concerning an important letter from Mr. Wharton, which he never received. Vexed at the ungenerous behaviour of the English towards his country; hopes the northern powers will no longer brook the pride and arrogance of that nation. Begs for news of America and suggests a way of forwarding newspapers. Has observed a blunder in all the translations of his "Theory of the Electrophorus," which affects the sense; will publish a new translation, with improvements.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Wrote some weeks before of experiments done according to Franklin's directions, with wires of various metals. Repeats his inquiries concerning an important letter from Mr. Wharton, which he never received. Vexed at the ungenerous behavior of the English towards his country; hopes the northern powers will no longer brook the pride and arrogance of that nation. Begs for news of America and suggests a way of forwarding newspapers. Has observed a blunder in all the translations of his "Theory of the Electrophorus," which affects the sense; will publish a new translation, with improvements.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 8; L in 3d P. 3p.; Lesease, -------. Mont Flanquin
    Desires to serve in the United States on condition that he reveive the command of infantry or cavalry troops.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Jepson, Benjamin. Boston
    Asking that payment be stopped on certain bills.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] February 8; A.L.S. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Sends him a foolish thing written for him; will be very angry if he tells anyone that she writes verse.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Nov. 1906, 169.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 8; Neufville, Leendert de. Amsterdam
    The disagreeable situation of Mr. Digges; caused by Mr. Trumbull's mentioning his name in his trial. Mr. [Winslow] Warren and Mr. Brailsford both taken up; reasons why they were suspected. Mr.[John] Temple's cautious behavior saved him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 9; A.L.S. 3p.; Willard, Joseph. Beverly
    Announcing Franklin's election as a member of the Amercian Society of Arts and Sciences in January, 1781; encloses a catalogue of the present officers, the act of incorporation and the President's oration. Desires to known what publications of merit have appeared in France during the last five or six years, especially in Natural Philosophy, Mathematics and Astronomy.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Introducing Mr. [John] S[c]haffer, recommended to him by Mr. Morris of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Girard, -----. Rennes
    In August, 1777, rented a carriage to a Mr. Vincent, an American, which was the last he ever saw of it; asks that the value of the vehicle be given him.
    [A. E. by Franklin.] Advises him to write to the French Consul at New York, with a power of attorney, authorizing him to recover the property.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 10; L.S. 1p.; Grand, Ferdinand
    Enclosing a bill of the Loan Office for acceptance; reasons why a bill is often refused.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 11; L.S. 1p.; Bũyck, Pierre. Gand
    Enclosing a letter from Mr. Thomas White, whose funds are in Franklin's hands; desires to know for what amount he may draw.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1781 February 11; A.D.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Le Ray de, fille ainée. Passy
    Receipted bill for carriage hire and wine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1781.] February 11; N. 1p.; Kéralio, Agathon Guynement, chevalier de
    Giving particulars about the patient's [the Dowager Duchess of Deux-Ponts] condition, great improvement but still seriously ill.